<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Lord Mayor and the Court of Aldermen at Guild-Hall Chappel on the 7th of May 1682 / by Francis Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1763</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12242334</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12242334</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Lord Mayor and the Court of Aldermen at Guild-Hall Chappel on the 7th of May 1682 / by Francis Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Macock, for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, II, 1-2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:56820:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Moore Mayor.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jovis</hi> xi. <hi>die Maii</hi> 1682. <hi>Anno<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Regis</hi> CAROLI <hi>Secundi Angl.</hi> &amp;c. xxxiiij.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to Print his Sermon Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning laſt at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel, before the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Lord Mayor AND The COURT of ALDERMEN At <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel on the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1682. By <hi>FRANCIS TURNER,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Macock,</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to His moſt Sacred Majeſty. 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56820:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56820:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir</hi> JOHN MOORE <hi>Knight, Lord Mayor OF THE CITY of LONDON: And to the Right Worſhipful the ALDERMEN his Brethren.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN I delivered this mean diſcourſe in ſo ſolemn an Audience, where the King's Ministers of Juſtice, with others of the long Robe met the worthy Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of this Great City, to begin the Term at the Church, with imploring the Bleſſing of God upon that excellent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which you and they joyntly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; I was much encourag'd to ſee ſo
<pb facs="tcp:56820:3"/> many Noble Perſons, and ſo numerous an Aſſembly practiſing ſo Religiouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand the Doctrine I came to Preach, joyning in the Publick <hi>Supplications</hi> and <hi>Common-Prayers.</hi> Your devout Appearance and hearty Concurrence in the Divine Service, gave me ſome Idaea of thoſe times a gallant Loyal Citizen deſcribes in a Speech of his (which for it's Eloquence might have flow'd from the Mouth of any Roman or Grecian Orator, and for it's Piety might have become the Tongue of the graveſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine<hi>—There have been Times</hi> (ſays <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Garro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way's <hi>lately reprinted ſpeech ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at a Common-Hall in the Year</hi> 1642.</note> he) <hi>that he that ſhould ſpeak againſt the Book of Common-Prayer in this City, ſhould not have been put to the patience of a Legal Tryal. We were wont to look upon it as the greateſt Treaſure and Jewel of our Religion; and he that ſhould have told us he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed well to our Religion, and yet would take away the Book of Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56820:3"/> 
               <hi>would never have gotten Credit. I have been</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in all the parts of Chriſtendom, and have converſed with Chriſtians in</hi> Turky. <hi>Why, in all the Reformed Churches there is not any thing of more Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence than the Engliſh Liturgy, not our</hi> Royal Exchange, <hi>or the Name of</hi> Q. Elizabeth, <hi>ſo famous. In</hi> Geneva <hi>it ſelf I have heard it extolled to the Skies. I have been three Months toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Sea, not a Day without hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it read twice. The honeſt Mariners then deſpiſed all the World, but the King and the Common-Prayer-Book; he that ſhould have been ſuſpected to wiſh ill to either of them, would have made an ill Voyage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though ſo goodly a Congregation as yours, whoſe Devotions I had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſerve that Day, was one of the beſt ſights I had ever ſeen, yet I live in hopes of ſeeing a better one Day; I mean
<pb facs="tcp:56820:4"/> the ſame Honourable Aſſembly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from your Lordſhip's Chappel to our Church of St. <hi>Paul's,</hi> which begins to lift up its head and to beg for its ſelf from every Charitable Hand, eſpecially from thoſe within the Walls of the City its Fellow-ſufferer.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhould forget my ſelf and the Duty to which I <hi>Exhorted</hi> others, if I ſhould not give this proof of my obedience to <hi>You that are in Authority,</hi> and I do it the more cheerfully to <hi>You</hi> that imploy <hi>your Authority,</hi> ſo well and wiſely, as <hi>Fearing God, Honouring the King, and not medling with them that are given to change.</hi> I ſhould not be true to my Text, if I ſhould not ſubmit my ſelf, and this plain Sermon to be diſpos'd of, as you have been pleas'd to Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am your Lordſhip's moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant,</hi> FRAN. TURNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56820:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the Lord Mayor, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 TIMOTHY ii. 1, 2.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>I exhort therefore that firſt of all, Supplications, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks be made for all Men.</p>
                  <p>For Kings, and for all that are in Authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable Life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Exhort therefore firſt of all—And I be-beſeech you Brethren to ſuffer the word of Exhortation:</hi> So the ſame bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> that exhorts us here, addreſſes himſelf to his Brethren of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael, Heb.</hi> 13. 22. No queſtion this in my Text is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to the greateſt of all Duties, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56820:5"/> the Divine Writer thinks ſo neceſſary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend at the higheſt rate, <hi>I exhort therefore firſt of all.</hi> Indeed here are two of our moſt important Duties joyn'd together, or as it were interwoven, and we are exhorted to them both;</p>
            <p>Firſt, To the due performance of the publick Worſhip and Service of God, for which there is all this Proviſion, <hi>that Supplications, Prayers, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions, and giving of Thanks be made for all Men;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe Offices of the Church are moſt particularly directed to ſecure the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Obedience due to the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whether ſupreme or ſubordinate, <hi>for Kings and for all that are in Authority;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The uſe of theſe good means is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to theſe two great Ends, the firſt of which moſt concerns our Temporal welfare, <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life;</hi> the ſecond reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es even our Eternal Condition, <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. And firſt we are exhorted to the care of Gods publick Worſhip and Service, on which we are now attending, to which the Apoſtle preſſes us elſewhere that we ſhould all of us be either Preachers, or at leaſt <hi>not hearers only but doers of this word of Exhortation, not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together as the manner of ſome is, but exhorting one another.</hi> For I muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56820:5"/> to you, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> is not writing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions here to his beloved Son and Diſciple <hi>Timothy</hi> for his private Devotions, but from his way of ſpeaking, (not barely, <hi>I exhort thee to pray;</hi> but <hi>I exhort firſt of all that Prayers be made,</hi> that is, be prepared, appointed, eſtabliſht,) 'tis probable that he is dictating as the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, and as <hi>Paul the Aged,</hi> directing this Apoſtolical young Man to whom this Charge is committed, <hi>that he might know how he ought to behave himſelf in the Houſe of God, which is the Church of the Living God.</hi> For <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> whom he <hi>beſought to abide ſtill at Epheſus</hi> was this Church's <hi>Angel.</hi> Therefore St. <hi>Paul en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns him what was convenient</hi> for ordering the pure Worſhip of God in Spirit and in Truth, for ſettling it in the Church where the <hi>Holy Ghoſt had made him a Biſhop.</hi> And it may far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear what kind of publick Worſhip is preſcrib'd to this Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> from what was practis'd in the moſt flouriſhing Churches in the firſt and the beſt Ages; the greateſt Lights of the Ancient Church undoubtedly left behind them the plaineſt Commentaries on my Text, in the pious <hi>Offices</hi> they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd for Divine Worſhip. True indeed what they left ſo well devis'd and deſign'd, has been corrupted ſince with <hi>Letanies to Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56820:6"/> and many falſe Doctrines are crept into their Devotions in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which would be practical Errors in us, and <hi>turn our very Prayers into Sin,</hi> if we ſhould joyn through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out with them in <hi>Theirs:</hi> though to ſpeak truth, they do not all pretend ſo much as to joyn themſelves in what the Prieſt is in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner whiſpering to himſelf in an unknown tongue, they neither hear, nor underſtand it. But I beg leave to ſay in behalf of the Church of <hi>England, when our Iſrael came out of Egypt, and our Houſe of Jacob from among the People of a ſtrange language,</hi> though we borrowed ſome <hi>Jewels</hi> of them, I mean ſome part of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Prayers, and brought them away; yet we have ſo accurately filed them, ſo carefully poliſht and freed them from the ruſt they had once contracted; thoſe that poſſeſt them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, do hardly know them again; nor will they own them now, being rather dazled than delighted with their preſent luſtre: ſo that we are in no danger of ſuch a Proceſs in Law, as 'tis ſaid the Egyptians commenc'd againſt the Iſraelites to recover their <hi>Jewels</hi> again ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred Years after, ſince they had proof enough in whoſe hands they were from the Book of <hi>Exodus.</hi> But our Book of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is no ſuch perilous Evidence in our caſe:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56820:6"/> our wiſe and pious Reformers receiv'd indeed, and retain'd ſome part of a Liturgy, (let none think ill of the Word, for 'tis a Scripture-word for the Worſhip of God in ſeveral places of Scripture, they retain'd I ſay ſome part of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy) that was us'd before the Reformation, but us'd before Popery too; for what they ſo retain'd, was moſt of it out of the Scripture, out of the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> and <hi>Goſpels,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Pſalms.</hi> And ſo we may ſay they receiv'd and tranſlated the <hi>Bible</hi> it ſelf, which was before in the ſame hands, but in a manner uſeleſs to the People, ſince neither <hi>That</hi> was allow'd them in our Mother Tongue. Nay, to ſpeak truly, we can hardly be ſaid to have retain'd any Prayers of theirs; rather we have reſtor'd the Pure and the Primitive Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and rejected ſuch as were truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly theirs, that were liable to any juſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions: we have kept to thoſe of the <hi>Old Catholick</hi> ſtamp, and laid by the <hi>New,</hi> the Catholick <hi>falſly ſo called:</hi> we have <hi>try'd and purify'd</hi> ours <hi>ſeven times in the fire,</hi> they roſe as it were from the Aſhes of thoſe Renowned Proteſtants who compil'd them, thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Men that ſuffer'd a glorious Martyrdom for being Proteſtants: they were the Men that <hi>ſeparated the precious from the vile,</hi> and that is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56820:7"/> admirable temper which God approves, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 15. 19. <hi>if thou take forth the precious from the vile thou ſhalt be as my mouth,</hi> and I may add the next words to determine the Caſe between our truly Apoſtolick Church of <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Rome, Let them return to thee, but return not thou unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now let no Man imagin that the ſame forms, if compos'd with ſufficient va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, may not be us'd <hi>for all men,</hi> whom here we are bound <hi>to pray for,</hi> or that they may not be conſtantly uſed <hi>by all men</hi> of the ſame National Church; and the more conſtantly us'd, ſo much the more devoutly with daily increaſing fervors, if all men would bring along with them a due intention of mind, and would practiſe the method of retiring within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by a good preparative Meditation: And conſider, I beſeech you, as to that objection of <hi>ſtinting or confining the Spirit,</hi> any mans Prayer <hi>for others,</hi> offer'd I mean in behalf of a whole Congregation, be it to the Speaker never ſo unpremeditated, is as much a form to the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er if he goes along with it as if it were premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated; nor ought ſett Prayers to be call'd a ſtinting of the Spirit, when <hi>David</hi> a Man after Gods own heart, has left us almoſt as many <hi>Forms</hi> of Devotion as he left <hi>Pſalms</hi> behind
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56820:7"/> him. <hi>Form thy Spirit by the affection of the Pſalm,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that is, frame and enlarge thy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> 3. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 30.</note> Soul to follow the ſame Holy Spirit that pour'd it forth. Alas! what's our Spirit in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of Chriſt's Spirit, for <hi>he had the ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure,</hi> and yet at two ſeveral times he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated and recommended the ſame Prayer, that is, the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Prayer,</hi> and in <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. 44. <hi>He pray'd the third time ſaying the ſame Words:</hi> And if it be ſaid, that a Form of Prayer can never expreſs the needs and neceſſities <hi>of all men</hi> who are here <hi>to be prayed for;</hi> 'tis anſwered, that no more indeed can all the moſt tedious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Effuſions be ſo particular. But yet a devout mind in the ſwiftneſs of thought, can eaſily apply, and ſufficiently extend the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Prayer,</hi> or a <hi>Pſalm</hi> to particular Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as a certain Father of the Deſart inſtructs his Diſciples how every one of them might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a kind of Pſalmiſt; <hi>That we may enjoy this Treaſure</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is neceſſary that we ſay the Pſalms with the ſame Spirit with which they were compos'd, and accommodate them unto our ſelves in the ſame manner, as if every one of us had compos'd them, or as if the Pſalmiſt had directed them purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for our uſes. Loving when he loves, fearing when he fears, hoping when he hopes, praiſing God when he praiſes, weeping for our own and others ſins</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56820:8"/> 
               <hi>when he weeps, begging what we want with the like Spirit, wherein his Petitions are fram'd, loving our Enemies when he ſhews love to his, praying for ours when he prays for his,</hi> &amp;c. To proceed then, our Apoſtle preſcribes in the <hi>firſt</hi> place <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> which are <hi>Letanies</hi> or <hi>Deprecations,</hi> for imploring Mercy and Protection againſt evils to come; next <hi>Prayers</hi> to procure the good things we ſtand in need of; then <hi>Interceſſions,</hi> as the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. moſt properly calls ſuch Petitions of any kind as are made for others, <hi>ſeeing he ever liveth to make Interceſſions for us:</hi> and laſtly, <hi>giving of Thanks</hi> the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent act of the Soul, and the moſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for <hi>'tis a joyful and a pleaſant thing to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> Theſe ſeveral kinds of Prayers were to be <hi>made for all men,</hi> with a Charity as diffuſive as the Love of God to the World, with a good will as univerſal as the Providence of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But I muſt not dwell on any of theſe <hi>Common Places;</hi> I proceed to that which is more particularly deſign'd and recommended by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> that ſuch Devotions as theſe ſhould be offered up to God, as for all men, ſo eſpecially, <hi>for Kings and for all in Authority,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Firſt then our ſolemn <hi>Prayers muſt be made for Kings,</hi> a cuſtomary Duty paid to the Kings of the Earth, and to the Royal Lineage
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56820:8"/> by the Jewiſh Church under the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and here confirmed by this Apoſtle under the <hi>New:</hi> And how even Heathen Emperours va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Church, is evident from the famous Decrees of <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> thoſe Great Kings, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 10. where their deſign of rebuilding the Temple, and reſtoring of <hi>publick Worſhip</hi> is avow'd to be this, <hi>that they may offer Sacrifices of ſweet Savour to the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and pray for the Life of the King and of his Sons.</hi> So <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> another mighty Monarch, but a Pagan ſtill, had the ſame veneration for theſe <hi>Divine Offices,</hi> the ſame ſollicitude that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions ſhould be made</hi> to God for him and his Poſterity, not without dreadful Apprehenſions of a <hi>judgment worthy of God,</hi> if his <hi>ſolemn and decent ſervice</hi> were neglected, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 23. <hi>Whatſoever is commanded by the God of Heaven, let it be diligently done for the houſe of the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: for why ſhould there be wrath againſt the King and his Sons?</hi> But then this Duty of <hi>praying</hi> for our Governours, is ſo well eſtabliſht by the Apoſtle's expreſs direction here, and by the conſtant practice of the moſt Apoſtolical times, as makes it a moſt indiſpenſable <hi>Office</hi> in the Chriſtian Church; and methinks 'tis very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable how St. <hi>Paul</hi> here has fenc'd and guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Duty of ours, ſo as to leave no room
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56820:9"/> for any to evade it; as if he had foreſeen there would be a ſort of Men (and they liv'd within our Memories, Men) who inſtead of <hi>praying for their King,</hi> would learn to pray againſt him: But then if all <hi>Kings</hi> according to the rule in my Text, ought to be <hi>prayed for,</hi> they who ſuppos'd their <hi>King was not to be prayed for</hi> any longer, no wonder if they advanc'd to the next immediate Conſequence, to make him <hi>no King at all:</hi> nor is it ſtrange if thoſe in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Kingdom, who of late had the hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs openly to excommunicate his Majeſty, and many others <hi>in Authority under him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering them over to Satan</hi> inſtead of <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> for them as their Governours, forthwith proceeded to refuſe them all manner of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> but now allowing ſuch Men all their moſt unjuſt prejudices againſt the perſons of their Governours; yet does St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this place oblige both them and us, <hi>to make Interceſſions</hi> for <hi>Kings as Kings, for all in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as lawful Magiſtrates,</hi> whether <hi>juſt</hi> men or no, he binds them to whom he writes <hi>to pray</hi> for the converſion of wicked unconverted Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Potentates: for it follows immediately upon my Text, <hi>For this,</hi> that is, <hi>this praying for all Men, for Kings and all in Authority, this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God and our Saviour,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56820:9"/> 
               <hi>who will have all men to be ſav'd and come to the knowledge of the Truth;</hi> where the Duty of <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> for the <hi>Converſion</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> of thoſe at the Helm of State, who all were arrant Pagans, is repeated and reinforc'd. Again in the <hi>8th verſe,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> is pleaſed to rivet this Injunction, <hi>I will therefore that men pray every where lifting up ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hands without wrath or doubting;</hi> methinks the Apoſtle forbids the Chriſtians here, to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cenſorious or ſcrupulous, as if their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the worſt of Heathens, whether <hi>publick</hi> or <hi>private</hi> perſons ſhould not be accepted, as he hath told them before, <hi>that this is good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable;</hi> and in my Text he expreſſes himſelf in ſuch terms, as may beſt ſecure his precept <hi>of praying for Kings</hi> from the <hi>moſt perverſe diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings;</hi> as if he had taken it for granted, that ſome might in time arrive at that height of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Inſolence, as to determine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, that they were in that caſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in St. <hi>John</hi> ſeems to diſpenſe with St. <hi>Pauls</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept here of <hi>praying for all men; there is a Sin unto Death,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John, I do not ſay ye ſhall pray for it:</hi> but St. <hi>Paul</hi> in my Text has provided e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt this ſuppoſition, though the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that hopeth all things</hi> were overcome, ſo that the Spiritual welfare of a <hi>Nero,</hi> or ſome other cruel Pagan and moſt malicious Perſecutor of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56820:10"/> the Chriſtian Faith were not only doubted, but in a manner deſpair'd of; yet ſuch a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is found (as no wonder if the Apoſtle has bounded and limited theſe great things exactly) ſuch proviſion is made, that as their Prince he was to be pray'd for ſtill, <hi>That they might lead a quiet and peaceable life.</hi> Thus it was in the caſe of that impious wretch <hi>Licinius,</hi> Colleague and Partner of the Empire with the Glorious <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> that ſame <hi>Licinius</hi> who became a bloody Tyrant, a Raviſher of Chriſtian Virgins, a Murderer of holy Biſhops, a moſt violent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor of the Church; when he firſt broke out upon the Chriſtians, the firſt thing he did, ſaith <hi>Euſebius, was to turn all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>out of his family, ſo</hi> (as much as in Him lay) <hi>miſerably ſtripping and depriving himſelf of the help of their Prayers, which they according to the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Fathers us'd to pour forth to God for him and for all men;</hi> no doubt it refers to my Text, and to this Apoſtolical Conſtitution; and the ſame <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſpeaking of this wicked <hi>Licinius</hi> now grown to the height of impiety, <hi>He pulled down divers Churches,</hi> ſaith that Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, <hi>and ſhut up others, that none of thoſe who us'd to frequent them might aſſemble there, and perform Divine Service to the moſt high God; for he was of opinion,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that they made no Prayers for him</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56820:10"/> 
               <hi>there, being induc'd to that opinion as being conſcious to himſelf of his own crimes;</hi> which implies ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently that they did make Prayers for him ſtill, though he thought the contrary.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, we are not only to pray for Kings, but for <hi>all in Authority</hi> under them, in which how the Ancient Church behav'd her ſelf, let one of the Fathers inform us, <hi>We pray,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for all Emperours, for their long life, for the peace of their Empire, for the ſafety of the Royal Family, for valiant Souldiers under them, for a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Senate, an honeſt Commonalty, a quiet World, and whatſoever elſe ought to be the ſubject of our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as he is a man whom we pray for, or as he is</hi> Caeſar. But is it enough that <hi>we pray for Kings and for all in Authority?</hi> ſome have been praying for them after a faſhion, that have at the ſame time been fighting againſt them. We muſt all pray to this end, and with this deſign, <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life,</hi> which is my Third particular.</p>
            <p>Now if the Church of Chriſt be ſo indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably bound to <hi>Pray for Peace,</hi> and if our lives ought to be anſwerable to our Prayers (ſince <hi>praying for Peace</hi> is but <hi>mocking of God</hi> without <hi>keeping the King's Peace</hi> too) then let not any pretend to be good Chriſtians, and ſound mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt's Church, unleſs they be alſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56820:11"/> good Subjects: Let none lay any claim to <hi>Godlineſs</hi> nor yet to <hi>Honeſty,</hi> whoſe heart is not ſet to lead <hi>a quiet and peaceable Life;</hi> let all <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical</hi> Power that exalts it ſelf above the <hi>Civil</hi> for its <hi>Deſtruction</hi> inſtead of its <hi>Edification,</hi> be lookt upon as a mere <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Impoſture. My aim is, firſt againſt the Power of <hi>Depoſing Kings,</hi> that has been often <hi>claim'd</hi> by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> maintain'd by his flattering Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; nay, by the Great <hi>Cardinal Perron</hi> himſelf, in a very auguſt and ſolemn Aſſembly at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris;</hi> a power frequently <hi>practis'd</hi> and <hi>exercis'd</hi> to the great ſhame and ruin of Chriſtian Kingdoms: Theſe ſeem to pervert the place that is almoſt parallel to my Text, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake; whether it be to the King as Supreme, or unto Governours as unto thoſe that are ſent by him,</hi> &amp;c. One would think they read the words of St. <hi>Peter</hi> thus; <hi>Submit your ſelves to me or to my ſucceſſor as ſupreme,</hi> and <hi>unto Kings as to Governours ſent by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is there not a many-headed Party of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries yet ſtill uſurping that honourable Name of Proteſtants, as guilty of owning the like Principles and of acting accordingly? Have not Three Kingdoms but lately felt it in the Death of our <hi>Holy King</hi> by <hi>wicked hands;</hi> in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56820:11"/> fall and bloodſhed of many a Hero in <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty under him,</hi> in the loſs of our <hi>Peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> in the decay of <hi>all Godlineſs and Honeſty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe have attempted to ſet one part of my Text againſt the other, whereas we are call'd upon here to <hi>pray for Kings and all in Authority;</hi> theſe have introduc't a diſtinction of taking Arms <hi>by the King's Authority againſt his Perſon:</hi> But as there is light and heat where the body of the Sun is not, for we enjoy light and heat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth when the Sun is in Heaven, and yet to be ſure where the body of the Sun is there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo light and heat in the higheſt degree, that is, in the fountain of them both: So 'tis true the King's Authority may be where his Perſon is not; but yet 'tis certain, whereſoever his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, there is alſo his greateſt Authority: So that to take up Arms by his Authority, yet againſt his Perſon, is indeed to fight by his Authority, yet againſt his Authority; which is moſt full of contradiction: And where his Perſon is not, yet if none act and if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be acted but by his Commiſſion and according to his Laws, that is ſtill by <hi>his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> 'tis the ſame thing, the King is preſent there. God imparts to them whom he <hi>calls Gods,</hi> as it it were a Ray of his own Attribute, to be by their <hi>Influence,</hi> in a maner <hi>omnipreſent</hi> within
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56820:12"/> ſuch a diſtrict and compaſs of their own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, <hi>Political Virtue</hi> goes out of them into others when they ſhall think fit to have it ſo.</p>
            <p>But ſome of the ſtiffeſt Defenders of our late <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Hammond<hi>'s pieces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. See</hi> Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate Temporali Pontif. Rom. lib. 5. cap. 7.</note> horrid Rebellion are agreed with the great Champion of the Papal Univerſal Monarchy, to offer another, and that a bolder diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and he tells us plainly that the Primitive Chriſtians wanted not <hi>Authority and Right</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt</hi> upon occaſion, and to make head againſt the <hi>Civil</hi> Powers, but that they <hi>wanted ſtrength</hi> in thoſe firſt Ages: So that for ſeven hundred years after Chriſt this priviledge of the Church to aſſert Her Rights, though it came to <hi>reſiſting</hi> of the <hi>ſupreme Magiſtrate,</hi> was, it ſeems, wrapt up in ſilence. A fair preſcription of ſeven hundred years, and of the very firſt years of Chriſtianity too againſt ſuch a Priviledge! In the mean time what becomes of his great <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> to interpret Scripture according to the Ancient Fathers? He that ſays St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul were not ſubject</hi> as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men <hi>to the higher Powers,</hi> for fear he ſhould be forc'd to acknowledge their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> are in like manner ſubject: I will not ask how he anſwers the plain words of Scripture, which he thinks to elude, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers;</hi> But I would ask how cloſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56820:12"/> does he keep to the Church for ſeven hundred Years, and to the Fathers, who he pretends are his Guides? See but how well he agrees with St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon the place, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>though thou art an Apoſtle,</hi> ſays he, <hi>though thou art an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, though thou art a Prophet, whoſoever thou art, thou art ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi> But will they ſay our Saviour himſelf wanted Power, or elſe he had exercis'd his Prerogative over Kings and Princes in the midſt of his Enemies? Did he want Power then, when he controul'd all <hi>evil Spirits,</hi> and <hi>caſt out Devils with the word of his Power?</hi> which is more than the greateſt Monarch upon Earth could do, more than King <hi>Saul</hi> could do to caſt out his own evil Spirit. Then, when he bid the Dead <hi>come forth,</hi> and preſently <hi>the Earth gave up her Dead.</hi> Did he want Power then when he commanded <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Nature?</hi> when even <hi>the Winds and Seas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd him?</hi> when he ſhew'd by his <hi>feeding</hi> ſo <hi>many thouſands with a few Loaves and Fiſhes,</hi> at how eaſie a rate he could have maintain'd and defray'd the moſt numerous Armies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>they would have taken him by force to make him a King:</hi> But he no ſooner perceiv'd it, than <hi>he departed into a Mountain alone,</hi> chuſing to be an Anchorite, rather than wear a Crown
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56820:13"/> and loſe his beloved Title, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49. 7. a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Rulers, yet whom Kings ſhould ſee and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, Princes alſo ſhould worſhip.</hi> He that had <hi>more than twelve Legions of Angels</hi> at his call, if he would but have <hi>pray'd</hi> his <hi>Father</hi> to ſend them, one might wonder what hinder'd him from giving the word to one of them, that came to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> him in his <hi>bloody ſweat,</hi> why did he not bid him ſtrike the Tyrant <hi>Herod,</hi> or thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſtrike the Roman Governour <hi>Pilate,</hi> but that he confeſſes himſelf <hi>ſubject</hi> to him? That <hi>Pilate had power given him from above,</hi> that is, in right of his Maſters the <hi>Romans,</hi> now <hi>lawful</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who had ſurrendred their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phi Antiqu. Judaic. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> Empire to <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, for the uſe of the <hi>Roman State,</hi> even the <hi>Power of Pilate</hi> as <hi>one in Authority under</hi> the Imperial Romans <hi>was ordain'd of God:</hi> Therefore you ſee our Saviour, not only paid <hi>the Tribute-money</hi> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but his Life-blood too; nay, he yielded himſelf to their <hi>Inferiour Officers,</hi> and menac'd the <hi>chief</hi> of his <hi>own,</hi> from whom this Power of Popes in oppoſition to Kings, is pretended to take its riſe; he threatned St. <hi>Peter,</hi> I ſay, with <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing by the Sword,</hi> for drawing his Sword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe common Souldiers the <hi>Governour</hi> had ſent to apprehend him. And was it only weakneſs that the Apoſtles forbore opening
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56820:13"/> and executing their Commiſſion as Earthly Potentates? as if St. <hi>Paul</hi> could not as eaſily have ſtruck dead the Jewiſh High-Prieſt <hi>Ananias, that ſmote him on the Face,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtruck ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ananias</hi> with his Wife <hi>Saphira.</hi> But that Husband and Wife were counterfeit lying Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, like theſe that we have to deal withal: they were no <hi>Kings,</hi> nor were they <hi>in Authority under them.</hi> Had they been ſuch, no doubt St. <hi>Peter</hi> was better taught by this time, than to have us'd them ſo roughly: For otherwiſe, could not St. <hi>Peter</hi> have inflicted ſome terrible diſeaſe, that ſhould have wrought immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon any Pagan Emperour? as immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately no queſtion as <hi>Elijah</hi> could tranſlate the <hi>Leproſy of Naaman</hi> to <hi>Gehazi.</hi> Where is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference then between St. <hi>Peter</hi> and theſe Suceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of his, for point of Ability to maintain the Rights and Royalties of the Church, if this of ſubjecting Kings and Princes had been one of them? But St. <hi>Paul</hi> though he was outrag'd then by that Mock-High-Prieſt (for St. <hi>Paul</hi> underſtood ſufficiently that there was really no ſuch High-Prieſt upon Earth, ſince Chriſt was <hi>aſcended into Heaven)</hi> yet that being no time nor place to argue that point, the Apoſtle on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleads he did not reflect upon that; allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon their ſuppoſition, that if he were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56820:14"/> High-Prieſt, or however, as he was a Magiſtrate, a Miniſter of Juſtice, he had done ill to <hi>revile</hi> him, and confirming it for a Chriſtian as well as a Jewiſh Law, <hi>for it is written thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil</hi> (much leſs then act Evil) <hi>againſt the Ruler of thy People:</hi> nay, he was ſo far from declining or diſputing the Heathen Emperours Juriſdiction over him, that he enters his ſolemn Proteſtation and Appeal, <hi>I ſtand at Caeſar</hi>'s <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat, by whom I ought to be judged.</hi> And if the Heathen Emperours were ſo priviledg'd from any deſign of <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> among the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, have they now loſt their Prerogative by turning Chriſtians themſelves? That were but poor encouragement for the Royal Converts. But did not the Primitive Chriſtians pay equal and greater deference to Chriſtian Princes? or did the Ancient <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, St. <hi>Peter</hi> had left them, dormant for want of Forces? Let the Apologies written by the Primitive Saints decide this queſtion, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they <hi>were ſubject for Conſcience ſake or no?</hi> There they ſet forth how great a multitude of Chriſtians there were in <hi>Rome,</hi> how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly they had it in their Power, if they were not extremely averſe from ſuch Deviliſh Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, to fire the City at any time about the Ears of their Oppreſſors, yet ſtill their Prayers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56820:14"/> and endeavours tended to this good end, <hi>That they might lead a quiet and peaceable life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſhould be our great labour in the ſight of all men, as well as our earneſt petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Almighty God, <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable Life;</hi> or which is all one, that we may enjoy a kind of lower Heaven upon Earth; for Heaven it ſelf is deſcrib'd to us a place of <hi>reſt and peace:</hi> I am ſure the contrary, that is, War, and the diſmal effects of it, are an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of Hell: For Hell is a ſcene of ſtrife and <hi>gnaſhing of teeth</hi> at one another. The <hi>ſword of the Lord</hi> does like <hi>Behemoth,</hi> that <hi>drinks up Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> but they are Rivers of Blood, when he bids it <hi>ariſe</hi> and go forth. His glittering Sword of War is ſeldom drawn without his flaming ſword of fire, that goes along with it, <hi>to lay fenced Cities in ruinous heaps.</hi> But though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more extreamly oppoſite to the mild and <hi>loving ſpirit</hi> that Chriſtians are of, at leaſt that they ſhould be of, than <hi>calling for fire and ſword;</hi> though nothing diſturbs their Devotions more than the <hi>Battle of the Warrior,</hi> with <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed noiſe</hi> and <hi>garments roll'd in Blood;</hi> yet there is ſomewhat elſe in War that makes a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian tremble, and frights him more, that is, the inundation of Vice which commonly runs along in the ſame chanel with that of Blood.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56820:15"/> This conſideration terrified him that durſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter a Gyant, the <hi>torrents of Belial, the overflowings of ungodlineſs made me afraid,</hi> ſays that man of renown: And yet in the ſtate of War it was neceſſary for him to ſet open a kind of ſanctuary for all comers, all that would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his ſtandard were welcome to him, <hi>the light and the vain fellows,</hi> as we read in his ſtory. He was fain to court and advance the <hi>Sons of Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viah</hi> that <hi>were too hard for him,</hi> becauſe they were <hi>mighty men;</hi> though <hi>Joab</hi> the eldeſt of them was fluſht in the blood of ſeveral brave and good men, yet ſtill he muſt continue Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the <hi>Armies of the Living God.</hi> But on the other ſide, how invaluable is the <hi>bleſſing of Peace?</hi> How well does the ſame gracious King <hi>David</hi> compare the <hi>Unity of Brethren among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> to thoſe two precious things, the <hi>Dew that fell from Heaven,</hi> and the richeſt <hi>Oyl</hi> that the Earth afforded? Even <hi>Seneca</hi> the <hi>Heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher</hi> apprehended and acknowledg'd the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of his being a good Subject, if he would be a good <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> or a happy man; <hi>Errare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 73.</note> 
               <hi>mihi videntur qui exiſtimant Philoſophiae fideliter deditos contumaces eſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sure</hi> (ſays he) <hi>they are miſtaken that think ſuch as give themſelves up entirely to the ſtudy of Philoſophy are proud and ſtubborn, diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Magiſtrates and Kings, or thoſe by whom the</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56820:15"/> 
               <hi>Commonwealth is govern'd; for on the contrary, none are more kindly obedient than they, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive greater advantages than from ſuch under whom they may enjoy a quiet retirement. Therefore</hi> (ſays he) <hi>thoſe to whom the publick ſafety muſt open the paſſage, before they can arrive at their end of living well, they muſt needs reverence the Authors of that good, as they would do their Fathers.</hi> Again ſays he of his good moral man, <hi>He loves thoſe</hi> by whoſe means <hi>he may do this in ſecurity—Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe protection he may ſtudy uſeful knowledge—thus the benefit of this Peace which appertains to all, is more highly ſerviceable to ſuch as uſe this Peace well. He will therefore own himſelf indebted to thoſe men by whoſe adminiſtration and care an entire repoſe and the free diſpoſal of his own time is allow'd him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if ſo much Love and Duty to <hi>All in Authority</hi> be ſo juſtly due from every Good <hi>Man</hi> that would <hi>follow after wiſdom,</hi> then how much more from every Good <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> but moſt of all from <hi>Us</hi> the Allow'd <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Philoſophy,</hi> I mean from <hi>Us</hi> of the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy?</hi> how mightily are we concern'd to <hi>Pray for peace and quietneſs?</hi> to Preach up this, not only <hi>for Godlineſs, for Honeſty ſake,</hi> but alſo becauſe the publick tranquillity does moſt particularly befriend and favour the privacy ſo neceſſary and delightful to <hi>our Profeſſion?</hi> we muſt needs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56820:16"/> reverence <hi>yours,</hi> and <hi>make ſupplications</hi> for you, and ſuch as you, who <hi>under the King are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> the great conſervators of our Peace, that <hi>execute Juſtice and maintain Truth;</hi> the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Law and Pillars of the Government, <hi>the ſhields of the Earth that belong to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But God himſelf is the fountain of all this <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> this <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>quietneſs,</hi> for <hi>the Lord God is a Sun and a ſhield,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> entitles him: a <hi>Sun</hi> to increaſe, to enliven, and add luſtre to all we enjoy; and a <hi>ſhield</hi> to guard and ſecure us in all aſſaults: But then remember upon what terms he is ſo, and upon what condition; it follows in the Pſalm, that <hi>the Lord will give grace and glory, and no good thing will he withhold;</hi> but it is only <hi>from them that live a godly life</hi> that he will not withhold it, or from them that <hi>walk uprightly.</hi> And ſo I proceed to my laſt particular, that we ought to pray for <hi>a quiet and a peaceable life,</hi> to this more excellent end, that we may lead it <hi>in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though there may be <hi>Godlineſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty</hi> without Peace abroad, (I mean it of thoſe good men that labour <hi>for Peace with all men,</hi> but cannot obtain it) yet there can be no <hi>peace and quietneſs</hi> either abroad or at home with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> 'Tis a caſe already
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56820:16"/> judg'd by God himſelf, <hi>there is no peace, ſaith my God to the wicked.</hi> There may be ſome <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> as the Apoſtle deſcribes them: there may be others that may <hi>dwell careleſs after the manner of the Sidonians, that were quiet and ſecure,</hi> as though <hi>there were no Magiſtrate in the Land to put them to ſhame in any thing:</hi> there may be a kind of Lethargic Dream, or rather a Mortal Trance, ſuch, as they ſay, Witches are caſt into when the Devil abuſes their Phancies with a Scene of Feaſting and Revelling; but a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Peace</hi> within, muſt have a ſurer foundation, and that can be nothing but Piety, nothing but <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Chaſtity</hi> as ſome render the Text, nothing leſs than <hi>all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> But then again, theſe are the natural preſervers of our outward as well as inward Tranquillity; for <hi>whence come Wars and Fightings among you? come they not from your Luſts?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. All foul diſorders in private Families, in great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in States and Kingdoms, are either from <hi>rioting and drunkenneſs,</hi> from <hi>chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs,</hi> or elſe from <hi>ſtrife and envy,</hi> ſo vile a Carnality that St. <hi>James</hi> calls it, <hi>the ſpirit that luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to envy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Secondly, there is a Supernatural Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion between <hi>Peace and Godlineſs, Honeſty and Quietneſs.</hi> For though <hi>Peace</hi> in this World is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56820:17"/> (I have ſhew'd) one of the greateſt and richeſt gifts and graces that God himſelf beſtows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mankind, yet <hi>Godlineſs</hi> muſt be acknowledg'd a greater ſtill, and the Supreme good that God in this life affords us. Now if we refuſe the nobleſt portion and deſpiſe it, and it's <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rewards;</hi> is there any reaſon that God ſhould continue his <hi>Grace</hi> of temporal <hi>Peace</hi> which we <hi>turn into wantonneſs?</hi> we are enjoyn'd to <hi>follow Peace and Holyneſs:</hi> they that dare <hi>Pray</hi> for the former without a firm purpoſe to purſue the latter, what do they ſay in effect to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God? Only, <hi>in this be gracious unto thy Servants, give peace in our time, O Lord, that we may make the better proviſion for our Fleſh to fulfil the luſts thereof. Scatter thou</hi> for our ſakes the <hi>people that delight in War, and ſtop the very rumours of Wars, that we may fill our ſelves with coſtly Wines, and that no flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the ſpring may paſs by us, that we may crown our ſelves with Roſes before they be withered, that none of us may go without his part of voluptuouſneſs, that we may leave tokens of our joyfulneſs in every place, for this is our portion, and our lot is this; that we may oppreſs the poor righteous man, that we may not ſpare the Widow,</hi> &amp;c. This is a ſort of Prayer that even the Heathen Poet thought too impudent to be offer'd aloud to one of their own tame Idols, <hi>Quod niſi ſeductis nequeat committere Divis; He muſt</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56820:17"/> 
               <hi>take his God aſide</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that prays at ſuch a rate,</hi> for ſure he dares not let any <hi>man</hi> overhear him at ſuch Addreſſes. Such a Petitioner deſerves to be repulſt, as <hi>Jehu</hi> fiercely replied upon the Meſſengers whom <hi>Jehoram</hi> ſent one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ask, <hi>is it Peace? what haſt thou to do with Peace?</hi> or rather he might expect in return to ſo prophane a ſuit, that ſome good Angel ſhould do as <hi>Jehu</hi> did to that wicked Prince his Maſter (but not till <hi>God had depos'd</hi> him) when he askt for <hi>Peace, Peace</hi> ſtill (which he meant to uſe onely for a Pander to the <hi>Whoredoms</hi> and the <hi>Witchcrafts of his Mother)</hi> he was anſwered with a bitter ſcoff, and then with an arrow to his heart; for he muſt needs <hi>ſay in his heart there is no God,</hi> that implores the Bleſſings of <hi>Peace and Quietneſs,</hi> but never intends the Duties of <hi>Godlineſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</hi> And ſure, we little value and eſteem ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe good things of this life that are the fruits of <hi>Peace,</hi> or even thoſe better things that concern our better part, that is, <hi>all Godlineſs,</hi> if we do not thus <hi>faithfully ask according to God</hi>'s <hi>Will,</hi> that we may <hi>effectually obtain</hi> thoſe Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chriſtian Priviledges; to uſe the words of <hi>Lactantius</hi> the Chriſtian Orator, <hi>Let us beſeech God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactantius ad finem lib.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>in our daily Prayers firſt of all, that he would defend thoſe whom he has made defenders of the State, that he would inſpire them with a will to continue ſtedfaſt in the</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56820:18"/> 
               <hi>Love of God. This is moſt beneficial to us all, to them in regard of their own Happineſs, to us in reſpect of our Peace and Quietneſs.</hi> Many, 'tis true, that have born the Sword and the Scepter, have <hi>done evil in the ſight of the Lord:</hi> the fault was none of theirs that <hi>pray'd for them,</hi> and <hi>their prayers have return'd into their own boſome.</hi> Yet even in thoſe Kings that have not been holy men, the Prophecy has been accompliſht in a lower degree, that <hi>Kings</hi> ſhould be <hi>nurſing Fathers</hi> to the Church of God. So the <hi>Prayers of the Church</hi> had their effect in part, when <hi>Adrian Severus</hi> and <hi>Antoninus</hi> ſate at the Helm, all three of them Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, yet far more equitable than their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, and favourable to the Chriſtians. But theſe <hi>Interceſſions</hi> of theirs were fully anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Royal <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> in the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and in other <hi>Chriſtian-Romans</hi> that govern'd the World; ſo likewiſe in many other Pious Kings and Princes in all Lands. Contribute then your <hi>daily Prayers,</hi> add them to thoſe that are on the file already, for thoſe great Bleſſings we pray for in our Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, where we beſeech God <hi>that it would pleaſe him to bleſs the Magiſtrates,</hi> theſe being the great means to preſerve <hi>Peace and Quietneſs,</hi> and the preſervation of theſe being ſo neceſſary to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56820:18"/> all <hi>Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> if the Apoſtle had bidden you do ſome great thing, would you not have done it to reap ſuch vaſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages? what, when he only <hi>exhorts that Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be made?</hi> what, when our Saviour has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, <hi>ask and ye ſhall receive?</hi> I do not urge you all to lead ſuch a life of toyl as theſe <hi>that are in Authority</hi> are fain to do; that <hi>we may lead a quiet and a peaceable.</hi> I do not ask every one of you to <hi>ſtand between the living and the dead,</hi> like <hi>Phineas</hi> with a <hi>Cenſer</hi> in his hand, but only <hi>to let your Prayers aſcend as Incenſe.</hi> Nor is any ſuch hard ſervice demanded of you, as was <hi>once</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be all day long at your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: He is called the choſen of <hi>God,</hi> becauſe he <hi>ſtood in the gap</hi> in all extremities, do you but <hi>lift up holy hands to God in Prayer,</hi> but do not think lightly of neglecting the <hi>daily publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of God, in the Church's <hi>Divine Service,</hi> do not refuſe to join with <hi>one heart</hi> and with <hi>one voice</hi> in all the parts of it: We do not <hi>know the things that belong to our Peace;</hi> if we think it may be ſecur'd any other way ſo effectually as by perſwading <hi>all men,</hi> if it be poſſible, and prevailing with them to be of the one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with this National Church; Give me <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat. Hiſt. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>in Vitâ Coſtantii Edit. Valeſ. pag.</hi> 144.</note> leave to relate a remarkable paſſage out of Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, to ſhew the miſchiefs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56820:19"/> thoſe men have fallen into that would not make themſelves part of the conſtitution, and of the ſetled Communion in the Church. <q rend="inline">The <hi>Arians</hi> under the Emperor <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who greatly favour'd them, perſecuted as well the <hi>Novatians</hi> as the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Chriſtians, both parties being Enemies to <hi>Arianiſm;</hi> the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> hereupon mainly apply themſelves to bring the <hi>Novatians</hi> back to the Churches Communion; and the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> tells us they were within a very little of being intirely united, if the <hi>Novatians</hi> ſtiffly adhering to their old Rule had not refus'd to joyn with them; therefore both parties were together perſecuted; at laſt the <hi>Arians</hi> prevail with the Emperor for his orders to ſend four Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of Souldiers into <hi>Paphlagonia,</hi> where they knew there was a multitude of <hi>Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to compell them, for fear of his Arms, to receive the <hi>Arian Confeſſion:</hi> But theſe <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> prickt on with eager Zeal for their Sect, arm'd themſelves with deſpair; many of them getting into a body, with long Scythes and Axes, and what ever came to hand, made head againſt the Emperors Forces. It came to a Battel, in which moſt of that party fell, and all the Imperial Forces, a few excepted, were; ſlain.</q> Thus in the Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56820:19"/> of God were theſe men permitted to give the leading foul example among Chriſtians, of waging War with their lawful Prince, after they had ſo long broken the Peace of the Church, and (however they weaken'd and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd themſelves, yet) obſtinately ſtood out and refus'd to joyn in her <hi>Prayers:</hi> For <hi>this</hi> (I think I may ſafely ſay) is the firſt inſtance of making any <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> againſt the Sovereign Powers by any that call'd themſelves Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Such was the fatal progreſs of that Schiſm, thus deſperately they fell who departed once from the Church, and would not be perſwaded to return to it. Therefore as ever you would be found good <hi>Subjects</hi> to your Prince, good <hi>Citizens</hi> or good <hi>Men</hi> in any relation, yield this to the honour of God, and to the ſecurity of the Government to joyn in theſe beſt and moſt Sacred bonds, <hi>the Publick Supplications and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayers for all men, for the King</hi> and <hi>all in Authority.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Exhortation was never more neceſſary than now, <hi>For Prayers to be made that we may lead a quiet and a peaceable life:</hi> 'Tis a generous principle, and beſides even ſelf-love would preſs it home upon you to make your own times (by <hi>your Godlineſs and Honeſty,</hi> for thoſe I have ſhew'd are the only means toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>with theſe Supplications and Prayers,</hi> to make
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56820:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> the preſent Age) <hi>as quiet and as peaceable as you can.</hi> Imitate our Bleſſed Saviour in his Agony, now <hi>we</hi> are in a kind of Agony too, and <hi>pray more earneſtly, and wreſtle</hi> with God until he have <hi>mercy upon us.</hi> Three Siſter-Kingdoms ſeem to joyn in this one juſt Petition, <hi>O pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem:</hi> methinks the Church of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> in which we were born and Baptiz'd, is ready to fall upon her knees, and ſtretches out her hands as a ſuppliant to you, that this <hi>Apoſtolical Canon</hi> may never be out of date with you, that <hi>firſt of all Supplications, Prayers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56820:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
